Finding Aid for Jerome J. Robbins Papers, 1861-1913 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jerome J. RobbinspPapers [microform] 1861-1913 1861-1865
Robbins, Jerome John, 1841-1921.
1 microfilm roll
Physician from Matherton, Michigan who served as medical steward and assistant surgeon with the Second Michigan Infantry during the Civil War. Diaries and correspondence concerning his Civil War service and two letters, 1863, from Sarah E. Edmonds Seelye, woman Civil War soldier who served under the alias Frank Thompson; also photographs.
852146 mf 325c
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These materials were donated in 1961 by Mrs. Alan Vierheller [Donor No. 3859 ].
The collection is open for research.
Originals of the collection are available. Access is restricted to the microfilm except with special permission.
Jerome J. Robbins was born on August 28, 1841 in Jefferson County, New York to John A. and Lorinda (Wales) Robbins; his mother died in 1845. In 1855 he moved to Michigan with his father and stepmother, who purchased land in Sumner Township, Gratiot County. From the ages of eleven to seventeen Robbins did not attend school in order to help on his father's farm. In winter 1859 he attended school at Matherton, Ionia County, and the next fall he studied at the Collegiate Institute at Leoni, Jackson County.
Along with several classmates, in April 1861 Robbins enlisted in the Second Michigan Infantry for three years of service. He mustered into Company I on May 25, 1861. Robbins began as a private in the hospital dispensary, later becoming a hospital steward. He was promoted to Assistant Surgeon on March 11, 1865.
When the Union Hospital at Savage Station fell into rebel hands on June 29, 1862, Robbins refused to leave his patients. He was taken prisoner and spent the next six months at Camp Parole in Annapolis, Maryland. After his release in December, 1862, he rejoined the Second Michigan for the march across Kentucky and Tennessee. During 1863 winter quarters in Tennessee, Robbins received a one month furlough which he spent in Michigan. Robbins re-enlisted, and mustered on January 1, 1864 at Blain's Cross, Tennessee. He was honorably discharged at DeLaney House, D.C., on July 28, 1865.
Following his discharge, Robbins returned to Michigan where he married Harriet (Hattie) S. Farnum, on September 3, 1865 (a variant spelling of Harriet's name is "Farman"). Having begun his study of medicine during the last two years of the war, Robbins entered the medical department at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor in the fall term of 1865. He received his diploma as a Doctor of Medicine on March 27, 1867, and moved to Hubbardson in Ionia County, where he built a successful medical practice, adding a drug business in 1880. Due to ill health Robbins gave up his medical practice in 1886, and in 1887 he purchased land, and turned to lumbering and farming in Ferris Township, Montcalm County, Michigan.
He and Hattie had three children: Ford P., Myrtle and Mabel. Jerome J. Robbins died in 1921.
The Jerome J. Robbins papers, consisting principally of journal and diaries, document his service as medical steward and assistant surgeon with the Second Michigan Infantry during the Civil War. The collection also includes some correspondence and other material relating to his civil war service and several portraits of Robbins. The collection has been organized into three series: Journals, Other Papers, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Classer, J. A.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1885.; Matherton (Mich.); Robbins, Jerome John, 1841-1921.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 2nd (1861-1865). Company I.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Participation, Female.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women soldiers--United States.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Robbins, Jerome John, 1841-1921.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 2nd (1861-1865). Company I.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contributors:
Edmonds, S. Emma E. (Sarah Emma Evelyn), 1841-1898.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Journals
  The bulk of the collection is a series of nine Journals (with entries from May 20, 1861 to August 6, 1865) which Robbins kept during his service in the Civil War as hospital steward and assistant surgeon with Company I of the Second Michigan Infantry. The journals focus largely on his religious activities and meditations, and also include descriptions of camp life, hospitals, weather, food, people and places visited, battles, and reports of war activities elsewhere. Most of the journals have lists at the back for letters Robbins sent, letters received, and the books he read during that time, as well as a topical index of the events in the journal.
  Of particular interest in the early journals are frequent references to Sarah Emma Edmonds, alias Frank Thompson, who served as a Union soldier, nurse and spy. She deserted in April, 1863, and by 1865 she had published a book of her war adventures. From these references, and from two letters in the collection which Emma wrote to Robbins, it was probable that she was romantically interested in Robbins, but the feelings were not mutual.
  There are two notable gaps in the journal entries. The first is from June 1-27, 1863, where the first twenty pages are missing from volume 7. According to a note in the donor file, the second gap, from February 15 to December 31, 1864, is due to a post-war fire at Dr. Robbins' office which destroyed at least one journal following volume 8. While the first eight volumes were consecutively numbered by Robbins, he did not write a number in the journal with entries for 1865, now volume 9.
  In addition to journal entries for 1865, volume 9 also includes lists of rations received (August 1863), government reimbursements (August to December 1863), medical symbols with Latin and English translations, and personal expenses (January 1865 to September 1867). There is also a twenty-page account of the September 1863 march through Kentucky and eastern Tennessee, which culminates in the Battle of Cumberland Gap. This account is rich with descriptions of the people, towns, farms and beautiful countryside seen on the march, as well as details of the battle.
  - Partial transcript of Vol. 1, Introduction andMay 20-August 1, 1861 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 1, Introduction andMay 20-October 5, 1861 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 2October 6-December 31, 1861 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 3January 1-April 26, 1862 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 4April 27-August 31, 1862 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 5September 1-December 31, 1862 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 6January 1-May 31, 1863 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 7June 28-August 27, 1863, (The first 20 pages of this volume, June 1-27, are missing) (Reel 1)
  - Volume 8, September 1, 1863-February 14, 1864 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 9January 1-August 6, 1865 and Miscellaneous, 1863-1867 (Reel 1)
- Other Papers
  The collection also includes Other Papers, most of which are clippings and papers from 1861-1867 related to Robbins' service in the Union Army and to his medical studies at the University of Michigan. There are five letters, two of which are from Emma (alias Frank) to Robbins. Of interest in the Miscellanea folder is a half sheet of paper labelled "secesh note" from Jackson, Mississippi, which seems to have been particularly sought out by Robbins. Also included in this series are photocopies from the pamphlet, The Great Battle, of those pages on which Robbins penciled in margin comments.
  - Letters from Sarah E. (Emma) Edmonds, alias Frank Thompson (Reel 1)
  - Letters, 1863 and 1865 (Reel 1)
  - Margin notes to The Great Battle, 1861, (Photocopies of those pages on which Robbins wrote comments) (Reel 1)
  - Clippings and Miscellanea, 1861-1913 (Reel 1)
- Photographs
  The five items in the Photographs series are all of Robbins. Although none of them have dates, two photographs appear to be Civil War-era: one of a robust Robbins in uniform taken in Washington, D.C. (probably 1861) and the other a more haggard likeness taken in Detroit (possibly while on furlough in 1862 or immediately following his discharge in 1865). The other three photographs are post-war, with the one taken in Ann Arbor probably being a graduation portrait (ca. March 1867).
  - Portraits of Jerome John Robbins, 5 items; (Two portraits appear to be Civil War era, with one taken in uniform; the other three appear to be post-Civil War.) (Reel 1)